<tool id="gatk4_collectmultiplemetrics" name="CollectMultipleMetrics" version="@VERSION@.0" profile="17.09">
    <description>- Collect multiple classes of metrics</description>

    <macros>
        <import>macros.xml</import>
    </macros>

    @VERSION_CMD@

    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        @CMD_BEGIN@ CollectMultipleMetrics
        #include source=$bam_req_opts#
        --DB_SNP '${dbsnp}'
        --INTERVALS '${intervals}'
        #for $prog in str( $programs ).split( ',' ):
            --PROGRAM $prog
        #end for
        #include source=$bam_opt_opts#
    ]]></command>

    <inputs>
        <expand macro="bam_req_params" />
        <param name="intervals" type="data" format="gatk_interval" label="Interval List" help="An optional list of intervals to restrict analysis to. Only pertains to some of the PROGRAMs." />
        <param name="dbsnp" type="data" format="vcf" label="dbSNP" help="VCF format dbSNP file, used to exclude regions around known polymorphisms from analysis by some PROGRAMs." />
        <param name="programs" type="select" multiple="true" label="Metrics Program(s)" help="Set of metrics programs to apply during the pass through the SAM file.  This argument may be specified 0 or more times." >
            <option value="CollectAlignmentSummaryMetrics" selected="true">CollectAlignmentSummaryMetrics</option>
            <option value="CollectBaseDistributionByCycle" selected="true">CollectBaseDistributionByCycle</option>
            <option value="CollectGcBiasMetrics">CollectGcBiasMetrics</option>
            <option value="CollectInsertSizeMetrics" selected="true">CollectInsertSizeMetrics</option>
            <option value="CollectSequencingArtifactMetrics">CollectSequencingArtifactMetrics</option>
            <option value="CollectQualityYieldMetrics">CollectQualityYieldMetrics</option>
            <option value="MeanQualityByCycle" selected="true">MeanQualityByCycle</option>
            <option value="QualityScoreDistribution" selected="true">QualityScoreDistribution</option>
            <option value="RnaSeqMetrics">RnaSeqMetrics</option>
        </param>
        <expand macro="bam_opt_params" />
    </inputs>

    <outputs>
        <expand macro="bam_req_params_output" />
    </outputs>

    <help><![CDATA[
    This tool sorts the input SAM or BAM file by coordinate, queryname (QNAME), or some other property of the SAM record.
    The SortOrder of a SAM/BAM file is found in the SAM file header tag @HD in the field labeled SO.  For a coordinate
    sorted SAM/BAM file, read alignments are sorted first by the reference sequence name (RNAME) field using the reference
    sequence dictionary (@SQ tag).  Alignments within these subgroups are secondarily sorted using the left-most mapping
    position of the read (POS).  Subsequent to this sorting scheme, alignments are listed arbitrarily.  For queryname-sorted
    alignments, all alignments are grouped using the queryname field but the alignments are not necessarily sorted within
    these groups.  Reads having the same queryname are derived from the same template.

    queryname: (Sorts according to the readname. This will place read-pairs and other derived
    reads (secondary and supplementary) adjacent to each other. Note that the readnames are
    compared lexicographically, even though they may include numbers. In paired reads, Read1
    sorts before Read2.)

    coordinate: (Sorts primarily according to the SEQ and POS fields of the record. The
    sequence will sorted according to the order in the sequence dictionary, taken from from
    the header of the file. Within each reference sequence, the reads are sorted by the
    position. Unmapped reads whose mates are mapped will be placed near their mates. Unmapped
    read-pairs are placed after all the mapped reads and their mates.)

    duplicate: (Sorts the reads so that duplicates reads are adjacent. Required that the
    mate-cigar (MC) tag is present. The resulting will be sorted by library, unclipped 5-prime
    position, orientation, and mate's unclipped 5-prime position.)

    Usage example: gatk SortSam I=input.bam O=sorted.bam SORT_ORDER=coordinate

    @PICARD_HELP@
    ]]></help>

    <expand macro="citations" />

</tool>